<chapter><title>The DB2LaTeX XSL stylesheets</title>
<sect1 role="frame"><title>What is it?</title>
	<para> DB2LaTeX are a set of XSLT stylesheets which generate high level LaTeX2e from your docbook document. 
	They do not perform any FO transformation, the only thing they do is to map DocBook tags into more or less 
	standard LaTeX (a recent installation of LaTeX 2e is required, with most common packages. However, in more 
	stable releases, package dependencies will be completely managed with xsl variables, making it virtually 
	compatible with basic LaTeX 2e installations). All the "styling" has to be done by modifying available 
	xsl:variables, overriding and	customizing templates, and in the last, by adding your "sty" files. </para>
	
	<para> More or less, they translate a <sgmltag class="starttag">command</sgmltag> 
      <sgmltag class="endtag">command</sgmltag> into \begin{command}. Of course, there are a lot of other things
	to do, like tables, bibliography and so on... but this is the main idea. 
	</para>

	<para> They are heavily based (that is, I started from a local copy and then start changing things here and 
	there) on Norman Walsh XSL docbook stylesheets. These stylesheets are published here with Norman Walsh 
	permission. Copyright and due credit is for Norman Walsh. Bugs are mine. However, bear in mind the fact that
	these stylesheets are NOT the XSL Docbook stylesheets. Thank you.
	</para>

	<para> They are "alpha". That means : it may work, it may not work. Your favourite feature may / may not be 
	implemented. I will be glad to accept patches in form of XSL code or anything :). Many thanks to those who
	have already sent me patches and pointed out some bugs.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 role="frame"><title>Copyright and Disclaimer</title>
<para>
	IMPORTANT: These stylesheets ARE NOT the official DocBook XSL stylesheets. These stylesheets ARE NOT
	maintained by Norman Walsh. Please, DO NOT e-mail Norman about any question regarding these stylesheets
	(he has been kind enough to allow me to use a great part of his work). These file ARE NOT part of the 
	XSL DocBook Stylesheet distribution.
	</para>
	<para>
	IMPORTANT: These stylesheets are ALPHA. That (among other things) means that the documentation IS missing.
	I have added here some basic instructions about how to install and use these stylesheets. Basically, you should
	be able to install and use these stylesheets by yourself. Otherwise, consider waiting until a more stable
	version is released </para>
	<para> XSL Docbook stylesheets </para>
	<sect2><title>Official Docbook XSL stylesheets Copyright notice </title>
<literal>
Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
files (the ``Software''), to deal in the Software without
restriction, including without limitation the rights to use,
copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or
sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following
conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

Except as contained in this notice, the names of individuals
credited with contribution to this software shall not be used in
advertising or otherwise to promote the sale, use or other
dealings in this Software without prior written authorization
from the individuals in question.

Any stylesheet derived from this Software that is publically
distributed will be identified with a different name and the
version strings in any derived Software will be changed so that
no possibility of confusion between the derived package and this
Software will exist.
</literal>
</sect2>
</sect1>
	

<sect1><title>Why?</title>
	<para>	The reason is easy. I wanted to have an easy/robust way to print docbook files. I have been thinking about this
	for several months and followed a lot of mail/news threads about this. I know about jadetex, passivetex, fop, 
	jade/openjade, xt, xalan, MathML, and so on.</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>A Short term solution until better solutions (passiveTeX, jadeTeX) 
		become more mature.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>An easy way to include LaTeX Math support.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Allows a way to print in more or less "out-of-the-box" LaTeX installations
		(well this is not true since you still need the JDK, xt, Norm's stylesheets, etc) 
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> Why not? They allow a migration towards docbook. the docbook source can be
		reused, and for today print releases, just translate into LaTeX, and change whatever you
		may want.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>	The basic comment here is: I do not want to discuss if this is a right approach or not. 
	You may have your reasons to consider using these sylesheets. I use them, because MathML is difficult! to type,
	there are not good renderers that meet all my requirements, etc., and because I needed to be able to distribute 
	LaTeX files. I think that FOP/PassiveTeX is the way to go, but unfortunately these tools are not mature enough... 
	Consider these stylesheets as another available tool that may/may not help you. USE THEM AT YOUR OWN RISK.
	</para>
</sect1> 

<sect1><title>How?</title>
	<para>	I have tested the stylesheets on a Linux box, only. I do not know if they work on other 
	platforms.</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Download the file 
			<ulink url="http://www.infres.enst.fr/~casellas/db2latex-0.5.0.tar.gz">db2latex-0.5.0.tar.gz</ulink>
		 </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para> Unpack (<literal> tar xvfz db2latex-0.5.0.tar.gz</literal>) the distribution. the docbook/latex 
		directory hierarchy is created, reusing Norman Walsh directory structure. Move them to your Norman Walsh XSL
		stylesheet current directory, so the <filename>common</filename> directory appears at the same level of the
		latex parent directory</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Use them as you may use any other  docbook xsl stylesheet.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
<programlisting>
(dir with norm stylesheets, e.g /usr/lib/sgml/xsl/nwalsh/docbook)
|
+---- bin
|
+---- common
|
+---- contrib
...
+---- html
|
+---- xhtml
|
+---- latex
        |
        +------ test
        |       |
        |       +---- dtd
        |       +---- figures
        +------ ent
</programlisting>
	
	<para> See the README file and the test subdirectory for examples. I am currently in the process of Documenting the
	stylesheets the same way Norman does,using the <literal>doc:</literal>namespace. Documentation is just in its
	barebones, but I plan to improve it.
	</para> 
</sect1> 

<sect1 role="frame"><title>Copyright and Disclaimer</title>
<para>
In order to make them more portable, the test XML files specify the docbookx DTD by declaring a SYSTEM identifier that points to the 
Oasis URL. This works but affects performance. Change the xml DOCTYPE declarations to reflect your local installation.
</para> 
</sect1> 


</chapter>
